<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An awakening voice to the Papists declaring to them the fallen state of the Pope from Peter's, and of the Church of Rome from what it once was : in love to the souls of those who have any uprightness in their hearts towards the Lord (but through ignorance are held in bondage) that they may be awaked, and see where they lie, and if any shall smother these things, lest they should come to the sight or knowledge of that people, let them take heed, that they bring not upon themselves the guilt of their blood / William Tomlinson.</title>
            <author>Tomlinson, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62896</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1845</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10231</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12590649</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12590649</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63899</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62896)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63899)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 676:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An awakening voice to the Papists declaring to them the fallen state of the Pope from Peter's, and of the Church of Rome from what it once was : in love to the souls of those who have any uprightness in their hearts towards the Lord (but through ignorance are held in bondage) that they may be awaked, and see where they lie, and if any shall smother these things, lest they should come to the sight or knowledge of that people, let them take heed, that they bring not upon themselves the guilt of their blood / William Tomlinson.</title>
                  <author>Tomlinson, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63899:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63899:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN Awakening Voice TO THE PAPISTS, Declaring to them The <hi>Fallen State</hi> of the <hi>POPE</hi> from <hi>PETER</hi>'s, and of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> from what it once was.</p>
            <p>In Love to the Souls of thoſe who have any Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs in their Hearts towards the Lord (but through Ignorance are held in Bondage) that they may be Awaked, and ſee where they lie.</p>
            <p>And if any ſhall ſmother theſe things, leſt they ſhould come to the Sight or Knowledge of that People, let them take heed, that they bring not upon themſelves the Guilt of their Blood.</p>
            <p>William Tomlinſon</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1673.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:63899:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:63899:2"/>
            <head>AN Awakening Voice TO THE PAPISTS, Declaring to them The <hi>Fallen State</hi> of the <hi>POPE</hi> from <hi>PETER</hi>'s, and of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> from what it once was.</head>
            <p>WHen I look back, and view that pure State and Condition of that Ancient <hi>Church of Chriſt,</hi> which was firſt planted at <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>Paul</hi> (as I ſuppoſe) that choſen Veſſel of the Lord, and afterwards Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by him, and Refreſhed and Conforted, and Inſtructed, and Strengthened by his Miniſtry, and by his Epiſtle to them, which is full of Heavenly Doctrine and Conſolation; and when I compare their State now with their Condition then, the words of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> concerning <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.</note> ariſe in my mind concerning <hi>Rome, How is the Faithful City become an Harlot! It was full of Judgment, Righteouſneſs lodged in it, but now Murderers. Thy Silver is become Droſs, thy Wine Mixt with Water; thy Princes are Rebellious, and Companions of Thieves, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one loveth Gifts, and followeth after Rewards; they judge not the Fatherleſs, neither doth the Cauſe of the Widdow come before them: Therefore thus ſaith the Lord, the Lord of Hoſts, the Mighty one of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>Ah! I will eaſe me of mine Adverſaries, and avenge me of mine Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:63899:3"/>
            <p>As is befel <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo it hath herein happened to <hi>Rome;</hi> That as they fell from a more Intire State, to a Corrupt and Rebellious, ſo hath <hi>Rome</hi> fallen from that Integrity and Purity which the Church of Chriſt there, was firſt brought forth in, to a Corrupt, Erronious, and Diſmally Dark Condition, and is become a very Sink of Sin and Wickedneſs: And therefore the Words of the Prophet do every way as aptly fit her condition, as they did the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> of old.</p>
            <p>You that are of her Alliance, look not upon theſe words as Railing; for my Heart is not in Bitterneſs againſt you; but in Compaſſion to you for your Good, it deſires to ſet before you ſomething of the Danger you lie under, and conſider it not; being involved in Darkneſs by Principles that have riſen out of the Bottomleſs Pit, but were never taught by Chriſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by are you held as in Chains under the Dominion of the Man of Sin, the Son of Perdition. Neither are theſe words Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as I ſhall make it manifeſt to you that have Eyes to ſee, and Hearts to conſider thereof.</p>
            <p>I ſay therefore, in plain and open terms, The <hi>Popes,</hi> to whom you ſubject your ſelves, they are not what you take them to be; nor can they do that for you which you expect from them: They cannot give you <hi>Pardon</hi> for your <hi>Sins,</hi> being themſelves in the Gall of Bitterneſs and Bond of Iniquity. Think not theſe Harſh or Raſh Words; I will prove them to be ſo, and that from <hi>Peter,</hi> whom they boaſt of, as if they were his <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors.</hi> And do you alſo learn with me the ſame Leſſon from <hi>Peter,</hi> that you may the better know both your own ſtate and your <hi>Popes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take your Bibles and Teſtaments, if you have any, and read <hi>Acts</hi> 8. where you will find, That when the Goſpel was firſt planted in <hi>Samaria,</hi> there was one <hi>Simon,</hi> who beforetime had uſed <hi>Sorcery</hi> in the ſame City, and bewitched the people of <hi>Samaria,</hi> giving out, <hi>that himſelf was ſome great One;</hi> to whom they all gave heed, from the leaſt to the greateſt, ſaying, <hi>This is the Great Power of God</hi> (thus the blind people took the Powers of Darkneſs to be the great Power of God) But this <hi>Simon</hi> the <hi>Sorcerer,</hi> beholding the Miracles which <hi>Philip</hi> did, and hearing the Doctrin: of Life held forth by him, believed, and was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63899:3"/>and continued with <hi>Philip</hi> as a right Diſcipie. Then the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> hearing that <hi>Samaria</hi> had received the Word of God, they ſent unto them <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> who pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for them, that they might receive the Gift of the Holy Ghoſt; for as yet he was fallen upon none of them, only they were baptized in the Name of the Lord Jeſus; then laid they their Hands on them, and they received the Holy Ghoſt. Now <hi>Simon Magus</hi> (as we may call him for Diſtinction ſake) he was with them and remained all this while as a Diſciple of Chriſt, and undiſcovered to be what he was: Well, how came he to be diſcovered? What was the Diſcovery of him? (mark it) even that carnal thought of his Heart concerning the Gifts of God, and the Myſteries of his Kingdom, that they might be purchaſed with Money, and he manifeſted this his Thought by his Words, in offering Money to the Apoſtles for that Power, to give the Holy Ghoſt, as they did. Then ſaid <hi>Peter</hi> to him, ver. 20, &amp;c. <hi>Thy Money periſh with thee, becauſe thou haſt thought that the Gift of God may be purchaſed with Money; thou haſt neither Part nor Lot in this matter, for thy Heart is not right in the Sight of God; repent therefore of this thy Wickedneſs, and pray God, if perhaps the Thought of thy Heart may be forgiven thee; for I perceive that thou art in the Gall of Bitterneſs and in the Bond of Iniquity.</hi> Obſerve, there was nothing at all objected againſt him of his former Sorcery, in Way of Diſcovery of his Condition, but only this preſent Thought of his Heart, <hi>that the Gift of God was to be purchaſed with Money,</hi> Now if that Thought diſcovered ſuch a Condition then, it diſcovers the ſame now, and at all times, and in all Perſons, whereſoever it is found. It is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Diſcovery, and by it <hi>Peter</hi> certainly perceived him to be in the <hi>Gall of Bitterneſs and Bond of Iniquity,</hi> and ſaw that his Heart was not right in the Sight of God, and therefore excluded him from having my Part or Lot in thoſe matters of giving the Gift of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Now if any <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> what is this to the Pope?</hi> I anſwer, He hath the ſame thought, therefore he is in the ſame Condition with <hi>Simon Magus.</hi> That he hath the ſame thought appears manifeſtly becauſe he ſets at Sale the <hi>Pardon of Sins,</hi> a Gift of God, which cannot be purchaſed with Money. If you ſay, <hi>He knows bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63899:4"/>and hath not ſuch a Thought as</hi> Simon Magus <hi>had.</hi> I anſwer either he hath ſuch a Thought, or he hath not. If he hath not ſuch a Thought, but knows better, and that the Gift of God cannot be purchaſed with Money, then is he the vileſt Wretch and greateſt Cheat in the World, to ſet that at Sale for Money, which he knows cannot be purchaſed with Money, and ſo to delude the Souls of Thouſands and Thouſands to their Perdition, in making them believe and depend upon his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and to purchaſe it with Money. If he hath ſuch a Thought then he is where <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was, <hi>in the Gall of Bitterneſs and Bond of Iniquity.</hi> And in the Authority of the Truth I declare him to be ſo, and that his Heart is not right with God, and that he hath neither Part nor Lot in this matter of giving the Gift of God, which cannot be purchaſed with Money. And whereas he boaſts of <hi>Peter</hi> as being his Succeſſor; by <hi>Peter's</hi> Words is he cut off from <hi>Peter,</hi> and grafted into <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> and ſo is Succeſſor in his Spirit to <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> and what help can you expect from ſuch a one.</p>
            <p>You that are learned among the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> for ſhame a wake out of your Sluggiſhneſs, and inform your People better, and let them underſtand the Danger they are in, who thus hazard their Souls upon a Man that is one with <hi>Simon Magus in the Gall of Bitterneſs and Bond of Iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let it be granted you that <hi>Peter</hi> was at <hi>Rome,</hi> and that he and <hi>Paul</hi> abode there, and inſtructed the Church there: What will this avail as to Succeſſion of <hi>Peter.</hi> It is not ſucceeding in Place or in any outward Concern that makes a Man a true Succeſſor of thoſe Holy Servants of the Lord; but only a continuing in the ſame Spirit and Doctrine. Now the <hi>Pope</hi> continues in neither, he is of another Spirit, contrary to <hi>Peter's:</hi> Nor doth he abide in <hi>Peter's</hi> Doctrine, as will be manifeſt from <hi>Peter's</hi> Words. That he is of another Spirit is plain by what hath been already ſaid, <hi>Peter</hi> judged him that thought <hi>the Gift of God might be purchaſed with Money,</hi> he judged him by that very Thought to he in <hi>the Gall of Bitterneſs and Bond of Iniquity.</hi> But the <hi>Pope</hi> being blinded and not ſavouring aright the Things of God, he doth not judge ſo of them that have the ſame thought now. If he did, he muſt needs judge himſelf to be ſuch a one,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63899:4"/>and all the <hi>Popes</hi> that ever have been, who have ſet to Sale their Pardons and Indulgencies; for the Buying and the Selling of the Gifts of God for Money ariſe both from one Thought, to wit, <hi>That the Gift of God may be purchaſed for Money,</hi> and ſo both are in <hi>the Gall of Bitterneſs and Bond of Iniquity.</hi> The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be not deluded in thinking him to be <hi>Peter's</hi> Succeſſor, becauſe he may be in the ſame City, where <hi>Peter</hi> once was, and there uſurp Authority over the Conſciences of People, which was never given of God. For he is a Stranger to <hi>Peter's</hi> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, yea and is groſly ignorant of, or rebelliouſly diſobedient to <hi>Peter's</hi> Doctrine, as I ſhall further demonſtate from <hi>Peter's</hi> own Words, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. <hi>Peter</hi> writing to the Churches, exhorts the Elders of them after this manner. <hi>The Elders which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you I exhort, who am alſo an Elder and a Witneſs of the Sufferings of Chriſt, and alſo a Partaker of the Glory that ſhall be revealed</hi> (now mark his Exhortation) <hi>Feed the Flock of God which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, taking the Over-ſight thereof, not by Conſtraint, but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, not for filthy Lucre, but of a ready Mind, neither as being Lords over God's Heritage, but being Enſamples to the Flock; and when the chief Shepherd ſhall appear, ye ſhall receive a Crown of Glory, that fadeth not away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From this Doctrine of <hi>Peter</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> differs in many things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He doth not make it his Buſineſs <hi>to feed the Flock of Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> did, and as he exhorted other Elders to do, to whom he commends the Epiſcopacy, or Care to watch over their Souls. And there was never any appointed <hi>Biſhops</hi> among all the Churches, by any of the Apoſtles, but in Order to that Work of feeding the Flock. But the <hi>Pope</hi> hath found out a new Work even to rule Nations with the Carnal Sword, as the Princes of the Nations do, which was in plain Words forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by Chriſt, Mat. 20.25, 26. <hi>Ye know that the Princes of the</hi> Gentiles <hi>exerciſe Dominion ever them, and they that are Great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe Authority upon them, but is ſhall not be ſo among you.</hi> What can be ſpoken plainer? Therefore <hi>Peter</hi> here exhorts the Elders, doth not thunder them with a Domineering Bull, as the <hi>Popes do,</hi> but exhorts them to their Duty. And <hi>Paul,</hi> he ſaith plainly, <hi>The Weapons of our Warfare are not Carnal,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.4. Let the <hi>Pope</hi> ſhew where he hath his Fellow among all the Churches of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63899:5"/>Chriſt in the Apoſtles Dayes or for many Generation after, where any were choſen <hi>Biſhops</hi> but to feed the Flock; he is grown as far different from the Apoſtles, yea, from the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſucceeding <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> after the Apoſtles Dayes, as a Leopard or Wolf is from a Lamb, as may eaſily be made manifeſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He differs from <hi>Peter</hi>'s Doctrine in deſire of filthy Lucre; <hi>Not for filthy Lucre,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. But the <hi>Pope</hi> out of his deſire of filthy Lucre, ſets at ſale what he accounts the Gift of God, as is ſhewed already, unleſs he will blaſphemouſly ſay, that the Pardon of Sin is not the Gift of God, but his own excluſively. And I cannot think that the <hi>Pope</hi> is ſo palpable a blaſpheming Miſcreant as to ſay ſo, though he blaſphemes in other things, which he perhaps is not aware of, and which may in due Place be minded, if God will. But here I deſire the Reader to note, that what is here ſaid of the <hi>Pope,</hi> is apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to any one particular Man of them only, but to that State of the <hi>Popedom,</hi> which makes them all guilty of theſe things that come into it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Pope</hi> hath turned his Back of theſe Words of <hi>Peter, Not as being Lords over God's Heritage, but being Enſamples to the Flock.</hi> That he Lords it over God's Heritage is ſo manifeſt in the World that I think few will deny it, it being ſo apparent that he Lords it both over the Bodies, Souls, Conſciences and Eſtates of People. I think Kings and Potentates may bear Teſtimony of this, as well as others, ſeeing they have felt his Power in diſ-throning ſome and enthroning others, and wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing attendance at his Gates till he was pleaſed to look upon them. Oh <hi>Lucifer</hi> whether art thou riſen! dareſt thou look <hi>Peter in the Face?</hi> that Holy Humble Servant of the Lord, whom thou boaſts of as his Succeſſor? No, that Pure, Holy Humble, Heavenly Preſence of <hi>Peter,</hi> if thou ſhouldſt behold it would ſmite thee to the Duſt; thou art not able to behold his Words without Guilt upon thy Conſcience, much leſs his Preſence. How canſt thou look theſe Words in the Face, <hi>Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as being Lords over God's Heritage?</hi> If any ſhall ſay, <hi>he is not a Lord over God's Heritage;</hi> let him ſhew how many Degrees higher he can be then he is, and how he can Lord it more then
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63899:5"/>he doth over Men's Bodies and Conſciences, thundring out his <hi>Eulls</hi> againſt thoſe that break from under his Yoke, and flee from under his Bondage for the ſaving of their Souls; and ſo ſetting his Subjects againſt them, and animating them to deſtroy ſuch.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And for <hi>being an Enſample to the Flock,</hi> he is far from that, from being ſuch an Enſample as <hi>Peter</hi> would have him; for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>Peter</hi> who was ſo well acquainted with the Lamb of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, would have Elders and Biſhops to hold forth his Example to the People, Meekneſs, Lowlineſs of Mind, a Saving Spirit that came not to deſtroy but to ſave. Now if we look no further then theſe principal things: How can a Proud Man be an Example of Humility? How can a Lofty Mind that exalts it ſelf beyond all Patterns of Holy Apoſtles or Biſhops, be an Example of Lowly Mindedneſs? How can be that ſmites Righteous Men, be an Example of meekneſs in Suffering for Righteouſneſs Sake? How can he who deſtroyes harmleſs Mens Lives who ſuffer for their conſcience Sake, be an Example of ſaving Men's Lives? He whoſe Principles lead to Blood, how can he hold forth the Example of Chriſt the Saviour, who came not to deſtroy but to ſave? but the <hi>Popes</hi> have been Examples of the contrary, of Cruelty, of Perſecution, of Blood. Therefore from their Examples and Principles, what Beating, what Stocking, what Impriſoning, what Tortures and Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clties, what Hanging and Burning with Fire and Faggot, what Maſſacrees and Inhuman Butcheries have been committed and acted by their Subjects? Oh, the Cry of Blood cryes loud againſt thee, thou Bloody Myſtery of Iniquity. And thou Froud <hi>Lucifer</hi> who art got to the Top-Stone thereof, and binds all the Building together and ſits as Head, how is thy Countenance ſtained with Blood? the World rings with thy Cruelties and Maſſacrees. Is this that wherein <hi>Peter</hi> bid thee be an Example to the Flock? Art thou his Succeſſor herein? for ſhame hide thy Face, come down and hide thee in the Duſt, and waſh thy Bloody Face, that thou mayſt behold <hi>Peter</hi> with a better Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance. Was ever any of Chriſt's Diſciples encouraged or countenanced from Chriſt to do ſo? But ſhall I ſet before thee what Race thou art of, Thy Name is <hi>Apollyon,</hi> or at leaſt wiſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63899:6"/>thou art grafted into that Spirit that is <hi>Apollyon</hi> or Deſtroyer, and quite out off from <hi>Peter,</hi> for all thy Boaſting of him, and thou art a Pattern of Blood-Guiltineſs, and not of Love in ſaving the Lives of Men. If any be minded to take up the <hi>Pope's</hi> Cauſe for him, let him ſhew where <hi>Apoll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on</hi> is to be found; or <hi>Abaddon,</hi> as it is called in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Tongue, both which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie a Deſtroyer; let them ſhow, I ſay, within all the Compaſs of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> (as it is called) or among all that profeſs <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity,</hi> where that deſtroying Spirit is to be found that exceeds all others in deſtroying, if it be not among the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> As for the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> (though they have too much tincture yet of that Spirit) yet they have not committed ſuch Cruelties and Butcheries of Maſſacrees upon the <hi>Papiſts</hi> as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have acted upon them; neither have they made ſuch Shambles of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt's</hi> Fleſh and Blood, as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have made of theirs in their publick Cities and Towns, where they have had Power. So that neither in Way of Judicature, nor in the confuſed Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults of Maſſacrees have they done like the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> When did they ever act like that which was done in our Nation in <hi>Queen Mary's</hi> Dayes, or like the Maſſacres done in <hi>Ireland</hi> of later Years? not to mention the many cruel and bloody Maſſacrees in Forreign Nations. Now tell me, where muſt we find <hi>Apollyon,</hi> but where the greateſt Deſtroyers be? and he is their King over them. If you can find out another beſides the Pope, or that Spirit which acts the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in ſuch Cruelties, I am willing to give Ear to it; but if you cannot, then know by whom you are acted in ſuch things, and whoſe Example you follow; whether <hi>Peter's</hi> or the Pope's, for they are not both alike, one holding forth Chriſts Example, the other a quite contrary, after which his Subjects walk, and therefore are they found ſo guilty of theſe things. For if he did hold forth the ſame Enſample as <hi>Peter</hi> did, his Followers would be like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded; as it was and is with the true Diſciples of Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, who take him for an Example, none of them are Deſtroyers of Men's Lives for their Religion.</p>
            <p n="5">5. One Difference more ſtill here appears between <hi>Peter</hi> and the <hi>Pope,</hi> from theſe very Words of <hi>Peter</hi> before mentioned. The <hi>Pope</hi> hath made a Diſtinction among his Believers, thus,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63899:6"/>ſome he calls <hi>Clergy,</hi> and ſome he calls <hi>Laity:</hi> The Flock or Body of his Believers he calls <hi>Laity,</hi> whereas <hi>Peter</hi> calls the Plock that believed in Chriſt, and were to be ſed and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed with the Word of Life, <hi>Peter</hi> calls them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Clergy,</hi> that is Heritage or Lot, ſo he calls the Body of true Believers God's Lot or Heritage, and the <hi>Pope</hi> applies that only to his <hi>Clergy</hi> who are in his Holy Orders (as he accounts them) thus he hath caſt off the Form of <hi>Peter's</hi> ſound words, and hath taken up another unſound Form of Words contrary to <hi>Peter</hi> of whom he boaſts. And the <hi>Proteſtents</hi> have not yet reformed themſelves throughly in that particular, but they ſtill call their Prieſts or Teachers Clergy, and the reſt-Laity; as much as to ſay, the Common People. Thus as the State of the Popiſh Church is fallen from its Purity, ſo their Language is alſo changed with it. And ſeeing the Pope (who boaſts of being <hi>Peter's</hi> Succeſſor) hath thus degenerated from the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Tradition of <hi>Peter;</hi> what ſafe ground can any have to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him in thoſe he calls unwritten Traditions?</p>
            <p>Thus you may ſee what a vaſt Difference there is between <hi>Peter</hi> and the Pope, who pretends to deſcend from him. 1. <hi>Peter</hi> fed the Flock, and exhorted the Elders who were to be Biſhops over the Flock, to feed them. 2. Not to ſeek after filthy Lucre (as the Pope doth) 3. Not to Lord it over God's Heritage or Flock (as the Pope doth) 4. But to be good Enſamples to the Flock (which the Pope is not) Such Biſhops as theſe <hi>Peter</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. And for any other ſort of Biſhops, as Univerſal Biſhop, or Lording Biſhop, there is no footing in Scripture for ſuch a one, from any of the Writings of the Holy Apoſtles and Servants of the Lord; but againſt them there is ſufficient Teſtimony of Scripture, as this of <hi>Peter,</hi> and that of Chriſt himſelf before mentioned, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.25, 26. It ſhall not be ſo among you, ſaith Chriſt. So alſo <hi>Paul,</hi> the firſt Planter at <hi>Rome</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat the Scriptures mentions, and the Lords choſen Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel which, 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 8.6. To us there is but one Lord, Jeſus Chriſt. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the World there may be thoſe that are called Gods, many, and Lords many; but to us who are the Church of Chriſt and his Servants, to us there is but one Lord Jeſus Chriſt; not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Univerſal Lord, or Univerſal Biſhop, nor any other
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63899:7"/>Lords under him, for to us there is but one Lord. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe Lords greater or leſſer, univerſal or particuiar, cannot claim any right thereto over the Church of Chriſt, from him, or from <hi>Peter,</hi> or from <hi>Paul,</hi> being denyed by every one of them. To whom then will they turn for their Foundation and Authority? Let them look to it as they will anſwer it before the only Lord that bought us, that we ſhould be his Free-men and Servants to him, and not the Slaves of Men in our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, as they are made in the Myſtery of Iniquity, <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon the grear, the Mother of Harlots, and Abominations of the Earth,</hi> Rev. 18.13.</p>
            <p>Let us view this Myſtery a little further which is headed with ſuch a Monſter, that is got up above all Kings, Princes Emperors, and ſee how it ſuits with that which was foretold of it by <hi>Paul</hi> that choſen Veſſel of the Lord, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. He ſpeaking there of the Day of Chriſt, ſatisfies the Brethren, that it was not at hand, nor ſhould come, till there had been a falling away firſt, and the Man of Sin, the Son of Perdition be revealed. And then gives them a little touch of him, that he might be known when he appeared. And thus he deſcribes him, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. of that Chapter, <hi>Who oppoſeth and exalteth himſelf above all that is called God, or that is worſhipped: So that he as God ſitteth in the Temple of God, ſhewing himſelf that he is God.</hi> This is the Apoſtles Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription of him that was to ariſe in the falling away, and was to be the Top-Stone in the Myſtery of Iniquity. Now let us make ſearch, and ſee where we can find one that anſwers this Deſcription like as the Pope doth. Who is there that ſitteth in the Temple of God, ſhewing himſelf that he is God, and exalting himſelf above all that is called God, or that is worſhiped? who is there that hath riſen in the Apoſtacy, and doth ſo beſides the Pope? I know that ſome honeſt people ſenſible of a Myſtery of Iniquity working Inwardly in the Heart, and not minding that which was to appear outwardly, do apply all Inwardly that is ſpoken of it; but I muſt deſire them and others to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider. 1. That the Myſtery of Iniquity here ſpoken of by the Apoſtle, was not yet riſen in the Apoſtles Dayes when he ſpoke of it, only he ſaw it working to get up: But it was to be let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or hindred, until he that did let was taken out of he Way
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63899:7"/>or he was an Enemy alſo that ſhould let it, and therefore was to be taken out of the Way; but the Inward Myſtery of Iniquity in the Heart was alwayes the ſame. 2. I would have them to conſider, that the man of Sin, the Son of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition which the Apoſtle ſpoke of, was not to be revealed till that which with-held the Myſtery of Iniquity was taken out of the Way. And ſo it had its appointed time of working, of getting up, of being revealed, and of being headed by that man of Sin; and alſo of being conſumed and deſtroyed, as is evident from this fore-named Chapter, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. I would not have any think that I ſpeak againſt the ſearching out of that Inward Myſtery of Iniquity lying and lurking in the Hearts of Men; but its my preſent Work to diſcover ſomething of that falſe Myſtery that hath riſen up as a compacted Body pollitick or Citty, and is headed by a particular perſon, in Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Body of Chriſt, and of Chriſt the one Head there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but under that ſhape a Devourer and Deſtroyer, and ſo hath his Name <hi>Apollyon,</hi> &amp; Son of Perdition. <hi>John</hi> calls him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.11. And <hi>Paul</hi> here calls him, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, both from one root, which ſignifies deſtroying, for he is a Deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and muſt go into Deſtruction or Perdition; and ſo <hi>Judas</hi> was called by the ſame Name, who betrayed the Innocent Blood; he was called, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Son of Perdition, but this muſt be another, and not <hi>Judas;</hi> for <hi>Judas</hi> was gone to his place long before: but this Son of Perdition was not yet riſen; and rightly may this Shedder of Innocent Blood have the ſame Name given him which was given to <hi>Judas,</hi> who betrayed the Blood of the Innocent, ſeeing they both agree in one Spirit of committing Murder; there is only this difference, that <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> had not a Myſtery to act under, but this hath a Myſtery of Iniquity to act his part under, which was not then riſen in <hi>Judas</hi>'s time: and ſo that which then went for plain down-right Treaſon and Murder, now goes for ſomething more plauſible, that it may not be counted Murder, but the juſt Judgment of God upon <hi>Hereticks,</hi> or the juſt Cenſure of the Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Hereticks:</hi> And then the people taught this bloody Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, That it is <hi>no Sin to kill a Heritick,</hi> and ſo the great Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> come to be looked upon as good Service done
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63899:8"/>to God. O horrid Myſtery to make ſo great a Crime, which is no where tollerated or countenanced by Chriſt or any of his Apoſtles, but utterly forbidden, and the quite contrary taught by them; I ſay, to make this look as a piece of Service done for God! So here the ſhedding of Blood of Innocent perſons hath got a Mask over it, and is acted in a Myſtery. The greateſt Crime how fair a pretence it hath got! and ſo they that are involved in this Myſtery, they come to be drunken with the Blood of Saints, and this ſtands as an inſeparable Mark upon the Myſtery of iniquity, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.6. Blood of Saints, Blood of Martyrs. But how doth this their Tenent and Practice anſwer the Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, and of the Holy Apoſtles. While he was in the Body, he went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout doing good, but did no harm to any, nor would ſuffer it to be done to any: And therefore he forbad <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> when they would have called for Fire down from Heaven upon thoſe that did not receive him; it is ſaid, he turned and rebuked them, and ſaid, Ye know not what Spirit ye are of; for the Son of Man is not come to deſtroy Men's Lives, but to ſave them, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.55, 56. But you ſee that the Myſtery of Iniquity is come for another End, even to deſtroy Men's Lives. So when <hi>Pater</hi> drew his Sword and cut of the Ear of <hi>Malchus,</hi> Servant to the high Prieſt, Jeſus would not ſuffer it to paſs without heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it again, and ſaith to <hi>Peter, put up thy Sword again into his place, for all that take the Sword ſhall periſh with the Sword, Mat.</hi> 26.52. And Chriſt told his Diſciples, that the time would come, that Men ſhould put them out of their Synagogues, yea and kill them, and think that in ſo doing they did God Service, juſt as they do under the Myſtery of Iniquity. But mark, from what ground? <hi>Theſe things will they do unto you,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>becauſe they know not the Father nor me, John</hi> 16.3. So that you may ſee that Ignorance (which among the <hi>Papiſts</hi> is counted the Mother of Devotion) is the ground of murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Innocent. And ſuch principles as this is part of that Smoak that hath riſen, out of the bottomleſs pit of Men's Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, and hath darkened the bright ſhining of the Gopel of Truth, and kept Men in the deſtroying Nature, ignorant of God and of Chriſt. And he that opened this bottomleſs
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63899:8"/>pit, and let out ſuch Smoak was a Star fallen from Heaven. The Angels or Miniſters of the Churches Chriſt called Stars, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1.20. Now this was a ſtar fallen, to whom the Key of the Bottomleſs pit was given, who had power to open the pit. This muſt needs be in the Churches of Chriſt, for there were the Stars. Now what is the Uſe or power of a Key, but to let forth or ſhut in. This Star had got that power that he could let forth ſmoke out of the bottomleſs pit: He could eſtabliſh Principles and Doctrines and Traditions of his own; and ſo open the bottomleſs pit of Men's Inventions and Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, for there is no bottom to be found. And ſo here riſes a ſmoak out of this pit which darkens the Sun, the pure Light received from Chriſt. And ſo the bright Sunſhine of Truth being darkened with ſmoaky Imaginations of Men's Hearts, and Wiſdom of the Fleſh, out comes the Locuſts out of this ſmoak, who have Power to kill; and ſo comes in the murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit again, which was once caſt out by the Doctrine of Chriſt and of his Holy Apoſtles. And the King over theſe murdering Locuſts was he that was the Angel of the bottomleſs pit, the Star that was fallen from Heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.1, 2, 3, 11. Thus you ſee whence was the reviving of the killing Spirit, which had been prohibited by Chriſt: It was from a fallen Star, one that was fallen from the pure Doctrine of Chriſt, and from an Innocent and Heavenly Life, yet retained ſuch Power from his place that he was in, that he could make his own ſmoaky Imaginations take place, and his fleſhly Wiſdom, which works contrary to the Wiſdom of God. Thus this man of Sin being exalted above all that is called God, or that is worſhipped, you may underſtand what Power he hath, and whereto it tends. It works quite contrary to Chriſt Jeſus and to the Holy Apoſtles, though under pretence of honouring them, he bears up himſelf in peoples Imaginations as Succeſſor to them, and the chief Father in the Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>People open your Eyes, and be not ſo befooled with that doating blockiſh principle, that <hi>Ignorance is the Mother of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion,</hi> but ſearch the Scriptures, and try all things, and hold faſt that which is good, as you are exhorted in the Scripture to do, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.21. And thoſe at <hi>Berea</hi> that did ſo when <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:63899:9"/>preached to them were commended for it, and counted of a more Noble Spirit then others, in that they would ſearch and ſee with their own Eyes, and not take things upon truſt; therefore many of them believed, as you may read, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.10, 11, 12. Is it likely that Ignorance ſhould make men more devout to God? Have not the moſt knowing Men in the World been alwayes the moſt devout to God? Search the Scriptures from end to end and ſee? Begin at <hi>Enoch</hi> who ſaw Dayes that are yet to come, ſo far of; was not be devout to God, think you, who had this Teſtimony, that he walked with God? Was not <hi>Abraham</hi> devout towards God, who fore-ſaw the Day of Chriſt in his time and rejoyced? Did <hi>Moſes</hi> want Devotion? Did his being brought up in all the Learning of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> or his great Knowledge in all the Counſels of God make him leſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout to God? Was <hi>David</hi> leſs devout, becauſe he made the Teſtimonies of the Lord his Delight and his Meditation? and doth not he pronounce him Bleſſed whoſe Delight is in the Law of the Lord? Was <hi>Daniel</hi> leſs devout by underſtanding by Books the time of their Captivity? O ſottiſh principle, contrary to all Experience! have not the moſt devout Men mentioned in Scripture been Men of deep Underſtanding in the things of God? for ſhame you Teachers among the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> teach them better Doctrine, and let it appear that you do ſo, by their Liberty and Boldneſs to ſearch into all Truth. For we know you do but lye if you ſay you teach them otherwiſe, whilſt they live according to that principle, and dare not ſearch the Scriptures. Do ye not remember that it was ſaid of old, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.6. <hi>My People are deſtroyed for lack of Knowledge?</hi> What, do you delight in the Deſtruction of people, that you keep them lockt up by ſuch a principle from ſearching the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures? Its a Doctrine to be abhorred by all Men, as fit only for Hell, and the Kingdom and Children of Darkneſs, who hate the Light, leſt their Deeds ſhould be diſcovered: But its not to be admitted among the Children of Light, who are not of the Night, but of the Day, who love the Light, and bring their Deeds to the Light, that they may be made manifeſt that they are wrought in God. If the Pope and his Subjects were Children of the Day, they would not fear the Light but love
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63899:9"/>it, as all Children of the Light do. But being in Darkneſs they love the Darkneſs, and its fit Doctrine for his Kingdom, to keep his Subjects and Slaves in Darkneſs, leſt they ſhould diſcover his Abominations, and ſo deliver their own Souls from under his Thraldom; for Ignorance is the Mother of Devotion to him, and to the dead Forms of Worſhip, and vain Repetitions and Traditions, which he keeps the People in Bondage to, for his own Gain. But let him or any of his ſhew from the Writings of the Holy Men of God where ever ſuch Doctrine was taught among them. Its he that hath the Key of the bottomleſs Pit that hath taken away the Key of Knowledge, darkening the Sun and the Air with his ſmoak: Its he that hath let out that Doctrine out of the bottomleſs Pit. Deliver your ſelves you poor deluded People, who are held Captive in his Chains of Ignorance, under that ſerpentine Fallacy, that it is the Mother of Devotion; for its only ſo to him, but not to God, who will have the Knowledge of himſelf to be as the Waters that cover the ſea, as he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and ſhall be fulfiled in due time. And therefore <hi>Peter</hi> opens to you the Way to Knowledge, but this falſe Succeſſor ſhuts up the Way to Knowledge. <hi>Add to Faith Vertue</hi> (ſaith <hi>Peter) and to Vertue Knowledge; and to Knowledge Temperance, and to Temperance Patience, and to Patience Godlineſs, and to Godlineſs Brotherly-Kindneſs, and to Brotherly-Kindneſs Love; for if theſe things be in you and abound,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.</note> they make that you ſhall neither be barren nor unfruitful in the Knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; but he that lacketh theſe things is blind and cannot ſee far off,</hi> and in that Blindneſs would the Pope and his Agents keep you by Doctrines of Darkneſs, leſt you ſhould ſee too far to be ruled by them.</p>
            <p>If you did but quit your ſelves of that one principle of Darkneſs, and with ſingle Hearts ſearch into Truth as the <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans</hi> did, you would come to ſee many more things of your own ſelves to be faulty. How eaſily might you ſee by the Scripture the horrid Blaſphemy of that Man of Sin, that ſuch a one as <hi>Simon Magus</hi> (who thinks that the Gift of God may be purchaſed with Money) ſhould claim ſo near Title to the unſpotted, pure and holy Lamb of God, while he is in the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63899:10"/>Gall of Bitterneſs and Bond of Iniquity; deluding your Souls with his pretended pardons for Sin to rob you of your Money. But indeed he cannot ſell you that, nor give you that which he hath no Power in.</p>
            <p>Many other things are corrupted among you if I may not ſay all, and you are far from that pure State in which the Church of Chriſt was at the firſt at <hi>Rome.</hi> But theſe things were firſt preſented in the Light before me to mind you of, that if it be the good Will of the Lord ſome of you may have your Eyes opened, that you may ſee to whom you enſlave your Souls, and may flee out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> leſt you partake of her Sins, and ſo pertake of her Plagues.</p>
            <p>And if any of you ſhall be incenſed againſt me for telling you the Truth, I muſt bear it. For I write not theſe things in Contempt of any, or to vilifie any particular Perſon, but in Faithfulneſs and Compaſſion to your Souls, to lay before you the State wherein you ſtand, enthrawled in your Spirits to a falſe Power, no Succeſſor of <hi>Peter,</hi> but of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> a fallen Star, the Angel of the bottomleſs Pit, King of the Deſtroyers, who hath his Name <hi>Abaddon</hi> and <hi>Apollyon,</hi> who is exalted above all that's called God, or that is worſhipped; and ſo ſeeing where you are, you that are ſimple-hearted, and have any Honeſty in your Hearts towards the Lord, you may be awakened to look about you, and to quit your ſelves like men, and may ſeek after the Liberty of the Sons of God and to ſerve him as his Free men, purchaſed by the Blood of Chriſt, from the vain Traditions and Injunctions of men which the Lord hath not commanded.</p>
            <p>Other things ſtill open themſelves before me, which I would not hold back from you, but as the Lord doth open the Error of them to me, ſo to communicate the ſame to you.</p>
            <p>Your <hi>Beads,</hi> and ſet number of <hi>Prayers,</hi> and <hi>Crucifixes,</hi> and <hi>antick Croſſings</hi> of your ſelves, they are all Works of Darkneſs and of the Night, and not of the Day, and will not abidethe Light. Think you that that God which ſearcheth the Heart and Reins, and ſaith, <hi>My Son give me thy Heart,</hi> that he delights in Lip-Labour, or in the Number of Prayers, inſomuch that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63899:10"/>you ſtand in need of a String full of Beads to count the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of your Prayers by? This is juſt to do like the <hi>Heathen,</hi> who think to be heard for their much babbling and vain Repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which Chriſt forbad to his Diſciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.7, 8. And which the Lord hated, and cryed out againſt by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets among the <hi>Jews. Iſa.</hi> 1.15. <hi>When you ſpread forth your Hands, I will hide mine Eyes from you; yea, when you make many Prayers I will not hear; your hands are full of Blood.</hi> And its in vain alſo for you, ſo long as you retain your Bloody Tenents, or Bloody Thoughts, to expect to be heard of the Lord. God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him muſt worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth, for ſuch the Father ſeeketh to worſhip him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.23, 24. And they that ſo worſhip him they have a better helper and remembrance then either Beads or Books. We know not what to pray for as we ought, ſaith the Apoſtle (to the ancient Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to whom he writ) <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26, 27. But where's our Helper then? Not from <hi>Books</hi> or <hi>Beads,</hi> but <hi>the Spirit helpeth our Infirmities.</hi> There was the Helper of the ancient Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and there's our Helper, one that knows the mind of our Spirit, and makes Interceſſion for us with groanings which cannot be uttered. There's the Helper of thoſe that cannot tell how to utter a Word, and their groanings are heard of the Lord, who ſearcheth the Hearts. And this Helper adminiſters Words alſo according to the Condition of the Heart, as there is need. But when the Heart is far from him, then to draw near him with the Lips, this is but an Abomination before him, and to offer up the Sacrifice of Fools, and ſo your Beads are of no uſe, but in the offering up the Sacrifice of Fools. I wonder that you your ſelves do not conſider the Childiſhneſs, and Ridiculouſneſs, and Folly of them; they are ſo Ridiculous Childiſh Bables, that they are not worthy to be mentioned by <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who ſhould know a meaſure of the Spirit of Chriſt in them to teach them to pray; <hi>know ye not that Chriſt is in you, except you be Reprobate?</hi> reprobate to every good Work. But I ſhall come cloſer to your Prayers then your <hi>Beads.</hi> Your Prayers themſelves are all Abomination to the Lord, with <hi>Beads</hi> or without <hi>Beads,</hi> by the help of Books or without them. Your private Devotions
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63899:11"/>or Prayers, and your publick Prayers, all are Abomination to the Lord, while your Hands are full of Blood, and your Hearts and Thoughts full of Blood. Your Principles are bloody, your Practices are like them, full of blood. Market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>places, Stones in the Street will witneſs againſt you, that you are a bloody People; your Priſons, your Inquiſitions will witneſs againſt you, and therefore your Prayers are an Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to the Lord. And it will not cure the Sore; it will not hide your blood-guiltineſs to ſay, they are <hi>Hereticks;</hi> they are Tares that we cut off, ſuch as infeſt the good Wheat; they are Troublers of the Church, and its no Sin to kill a <hi>Heretick.</hi> So indeed you are taught, as by your Practices hath ſufficiently appeared to the World. But have you never read what Chriſt ſaid to thoſe his ſervants who enquired of him, whether they ſhould pluck up the Tares or no, <hi>Math.</hi> 13.29, 30. How he forbad them, ſaying, <hi>Nay—Let both grow together until the Harveſt,</hi> and then he explains to his Diſciples when the Harveſt ſhall be, and whoſe Work it ſhall be to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate the Tares from the Wheat. The Parable begins <hi>ver.</hi> 24. and ends with <hi>ver.</hi> 30. And Chriſt's own Explanation of that Parable you may read from <hi>ver.</hi> 36. to <hi>ver.</hi> 43. where he ſaith plainly, <hi>The Harveſt is the End of the World, and the Reapers</hi> (who are to do that Work) <hi>are the Angels.</hi> And ſo he reſerves that Work for them who ſhall be ſufficiently able to diſtinguiſh Tares from Wheat, <hi>Heroticks</hi> from true <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi> And therefore till then they are to be let alone in the Field (which is the World.)</p>
            <p>Now here are two contrary Leſſons, your Maſters ſay, you may kill <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and ſo inſtigate you thereto, and make you believe that you do good Service to God and the Church thereby. But Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, and our alone Saviour ſaith, <hi>No, let them alone untill the Harveſt.</hi> Now chuſe which Maſter you will cleave to; for you cannot ſerve both in their contrary Precepts. If Chriſt Jeſus be your Saviour then follow him; but if the Pope and his Companions be your Saviours then follow them, and continue in your bloody Principles, and Practices, and bloody Spirits, and ſee if they can ſave you, who cannot ſave themſelves, nor give ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63899:11"/>unto God for what they do, ſeeing they go contrary to his Commands; See if they can make your Prayers accepted, who are Men of Blood themſelves, and whoſe own Prayers are therefore an abhorring to the Lord. Your Church is a Church of Blood, and therefore all your Prayers are an Abomination to the Lord. Repent therefore in the firſt place, of your Blood-guiltineſs, whoſoever of you hath but conſented in your Hearts to that Act of killing for Religion; and cleanſe your Spirits from that Scarlet Dye, whoſoever you be; and come before the Lord with Love in your Hearts for your Enemies; and then your Prayers may find Acceſs to the Throne of Grace. But if you come otherwiſe with a Principle of killing and deſtroying in your Hearts, you do but pray for your own Deſtruction, when you ſay, <hi>Forgive us, as we forgive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor will your Crucifixes, or Croſſings of your ſelves pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail any thing with the Lord, being but empty ſhaddows of things, whereby you evade the true Croſs of Chriſt, and caſt it off your Necks. Its true, <hi>Conſtantine the great</hi> (ſo called) <hi>he, as its recorded of him, uſed the Sign of the Croſs in his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns in Battel, and that properly; to hold out againſt the Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of</hi> Chriſtianity, <hi>that he openly owned and embraced that</hi> Chriſt <hi>who was crucified upon the Croſs, whom the Enemies therefore vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified, becauſe of that manner of Death, and crucified ſome of his Followers after the ſame manner in contempt of him. But he was to honour him under the ſame Sign which they deſpiſed him for. We may believe that that thing was prompted to him from the Lord; But its good to conſider his condition at that time, and how ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able it was to his Condition and the times. Its true, there was that in his Heart that favoured and cheriſhed the</hi> Chriſtians, <hi>and which abhorred the Perſecutions of the other Emperors (for then was the</hi> Roman <hi>Empire divided among four, of which</hi> Conſtantine <hi>was one) And eſpecially his Heart roſe againſt the deteſtable Wickedneſs of one of the Emperors called</hi> Maxentius, <hi>who raviſhed the Citizens Wives, and put many to Death unjuſtly. And ſo</hi> Conſtantine <hi>thinking how to remove that Tyrant, caſt in his Mind, what God he ſhould chuſe to himſelf to call upon as a Helper in that Work, in going againſt that Tyrant.</hi> And in this his Deliberation and Care to effect this Work, its ſaid, <hi>That abright Pillar ſhining in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63899:12"/>was repreſented to him in form of a Croſs, with this Inſcription, In hoc vince,</hi> that is, <hi>In this overcome.</hi> You may obſerve, that he was wavering in his mind, what God to turn to for a Helper, being yet ignorant of the true Helper; and therefore the Lord anſwered the Simplicity of his Heart by a Sign, ſhewing him, to whom to turn; and alſo gave him that <hi>deſpiſed Name of Chriſt crucified,</hi> to war under; and by the outward Sign of the Croſs, to hold forth in the World the Crucified Chriſt, being at that day ſo deſpiſed. And ſo being obedient to the Lord in holding forth that Name, and owning him openly by that Sign, the Lord made him victorious and great. But now ever after to make an Idol of the Croſs, as if the Croſs had done all for <hi>Conſtantine;</hi> this is juſt like the doings of the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> for whom the Lord commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſet up a fore-running Sign of Chriſt crucified, even the Serpent in the Wilderneſs; by looking up to which they ſhould be healed who were ſtung with fiery Serpents; for after the uſe of that brazen Serpent, and ſervice of it was ended, they went a who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring after it, admiring it, and idolizing it, as if it had hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by its own Vertue. And juſt ſo do you, after the Sign of the Croſs, when the ſervice of it is finiſhed. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> took the brazen Serpent and ſtampt it to Powder, ſo ought the outward ſign of the Croſs which you ſo Idolize be dealt with. The Croſs of Chriſt which you ought to take up dayly, and bear about you, is, the Croſſing of your own corrupt Wills and Affections, and fleſhly and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Liberties, and Looſeneſs of the Tongue to utter Vanity: You ought to croſs your Wills in laying down your Necks to the Yoak of Chriſt, in bearing the Reproaches of looſe and ungodly Walkers, who ſcoff at a Holy and Innocent Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; and alſo in bearing the Oppoſition and Contradiction of ſuch as may traduce you for withdrawing from thoſe who worſhip God after the Traditions of men, and have a Form of Godlineſs, but deny the Power thereof. In theſe and ſuch like things as theſe doth the Croſs of Chriſt lie, not in a Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Picture of the Croſs, or antick ſigning of your ſelves, as if the Power lay in that. Therefore become Men in Underſtanding, and offer unto God a rational ſacrifice, laying aſide Childiſh things.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:63899:12"/>
            <p>I have ſomething ſtill before me, to offer unto you for your good, for my ſoul intirely deſires your deliverance from under your bondage that you are in to the man of ſin. Your Images and Pictures, wherefore doe you uſe them in your approaches to the All-ſeeing God, who is preſent in all places, and ſearches all hearts, and knows the thoughts of the heart? Wherefore, I ſay, doe you uſe them? If you worſhip them, then are you Idolaters. If you ſay, nay, we worſhip them not, but only uſe them, as repreſentations, to put us in mind of God, and of Chriſt Jeſus our Saviour; then be ye witneſſes againſt your ſelves. That Chriſt Jeſus dwells not in your hearts to imprint the living remembrance of himſelf in you. Are you members of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, which is ſo ſurely built upon the Truth, that all deſerve to be burnt as Hereticks that ſubmit not to your Traditions? And are you ſo forgetfull of the Lord that you need Images to mind you of him? Be witneſſes. I ſay, againſt your ſelves, that God dwells not in you, nor you in him; and that you have loſt the Union which the Saints once had and yet have with God; who therefore ſtand in no need of ſuch things to put them in mind of the Lord; for his loving pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in them keeps their minds and hearts with the Lord. Therefore you are become ſtrangers to God; and to the holy Anointing which keeps abiding in him. And herein you are degenerated from the firſt ſtate of Believers, and of the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church at Rome,</hi> who were led of the Spirit, and had the witneſs of the Spirit, witneſſing with their Spirits, that they were the Sons of God; and ſo walking with God in the Spirit they needed no ſuch thing to keep them in mind of God, nor did they uſe any ſuch things.</p>
            <p>But wherefore, I ſay again, do you ſet Images and Pictures before you, when you pray to the Lord? Is it to divert your minds that you ſhould mind ſomething elſe beſides the Lord in your prayers, leſt you ſhould ſerve the Lord with all your heart, and with all your mind; or you ſet ſuch things as me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diators between God and you? If ſo, then know that you have Choſen to your ſelves mediators which God hath not appoir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: but you have ſet up the devices of your own hearts. If it be only to put you in mind of the Lord, then when you
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63899:13"/>are put in mind of him and go to pray to him turn from them, and put them out of your ſight, leſt they divert your minds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But wherefore muſt the Image of Mary the Mother of Jeſus, and the Image of Peter,</hi> or any other holy ſervant of Chriſt be ſet before you when you pray? Do you worſhip their Pictures; Or do you pray to the Picture, or to them? If you worſhip their Pictures, or pray to their Pictures, you are Idolaters. If you pray to them that are repreſented by the Pictures, you make Gods of them, and ſo ſtill you are Idolaters. And you give them that worſhip which is only due to God, &amp; which <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> durſt not take to themſelves, when the men of <hi>Licaonia</hi> would have done Sacrifice to them, but rent their clothes and ran in among them, to conſtrain them, as ſoon as they perceived it. If you ſay, That was Sacrifice, but this is prayer to them. I Anſwer, Is not prayer Sacrifice? Is it not preferred before burnt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice? Is it not above the burning of a Lamb, or an Ox, or above the burning of Incenſe? Is not the thing it ſelf more then the Type or Shaddow? The Type ſometimes is an abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, though of Gods own appointment, as Sacrifices, and burnt Offerings, and burning of Incenſe was, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.3. But the true Incenſe, the prayers of Saints never is ſo. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore prayer is greater then ſacrifice, which the Apoſtles abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be done to them: Nor would <hi>Petor</hi> ſuffer <hi>Cornelius</hi> to worſhip him, but took him up, ſaying, ſtand up, I my ſelf alſo am a man, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.25, 26. Neither would the Angel of the Lord ſuffer John to worſhip him, when he fell down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his feet to worſhip, <hi>but ſaith to him, See thou do it not, for I am thy fellow Servant, and of thy brethren the Prophets, and of them which keep the ſayings of this Book: Worſhip God, Rev.</hi> 22.9. You may hence learn, if you be Ignorant of it, That Angels, and the Prophets, and others that keep the ſayings of this Book are all Fellow-Servants to God. And becauſe they are Fellow-Servants they ought not to worſhip one another; the leaſt Member is not to worſhip the greateſt, neither Saint nor An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel. Thats the reaſon the Angel gives why he would not ſuffer <hi>John</hi> to fall down before his Feet to worſhip; becauſe he was but his fellow-Servant. Do you think that <hi>Mary,</hi> or <hi>Peter,</hi> or <hi>John,</hi> or any other holy Servants of the Lord would not ſay
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63899:13"/>the like, if they were preſent, and ſee you falling down to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip before their Feet, and to pray to them? would they take the Honour of God to themſelves any more then the Angel did? No ſurely, they would not ſtand between God and his Honour any more then the Angel did. Your falling down to worſhip them ſhews, that you are ignorant of that pure and holy Spirit that dwelt and dwelleth in the Saints, which makes them Jealous of ſuch actions, leſt God thereby ſhould be robbed, of his Glory. There's no right Spirit will deſire it, or delight in it, but be afraid of it.</p>
            <p>Its the ſpirit of the Devil that delights to be worſhipped, who would have had Chriſt to fall down and worſhip him; and now would have Men to fall down and worſhip any thing but God; and its that ſpirit which Men gratify, when they worſhip any other but the Lord. Therefore turn from this Idolatry, and worſhip the only Lord God who made you, the Heavens, and the Earth, and all the Hoſt of them, even all the Angels and Holy Men that are in Glory, who themſelves fall down, and worſhip him, and dare not take to themſelves that which belongs to God.</p>
            <p>Will you make Gods of Men, and imagine them to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent (as God is) over the Face of the Earth? It may be ten thouſand Perſons or more, in ſeveral parts of the Earth, as far diſtant ſome of them, as the Eaſt is from the Weſt, may be all praying at once to the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> or to <hi>Peter,</hi> or ſome other; do you think them to be preſent in all Places to hear their Prayers, as God himſelf is preſent? If you do ſo think of them then how differ they from God in his Omni-preſence and Omni-ſcience. If you ſay, No, they are not preſent every where as God is; then (if they could hear Prayer) yet how many of theſe muſt pray in vain to thoſe who cannot hear them? I thus follow you to convince you of your Error, if it may be. Away, away with your abominable Idolatry, in making God's of Men, and praying unto them as if they were every where; and let your Hearts turn to the Lord, who hath created you, and in whom you live and move and have your being, who upholds all things by the Word of this Power, and who is preſent in all your Hearts, and Reins, and ſees
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63899:14"/>the Intents and Purpoſes of your Hearts. Who though he made all things, and the Heaven be his Throne, and the Earth his Foot-ſtool; yet humbleth he himſelf to draw near unto his Creature; <hi>and to this Man will I look</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that is poor and of a contrite Spirit, and trembleth at my Word, Iſa.</hi> 66.1, 2. Therefore none need to be diſcouraged, and pretend to make Mediators of the Saints, as if they themſelves were unworthy; for the poorer in Spirit that any one is, the nearer doth the Lord draw to that man. And he hath appointed no Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator between himſelf and us, but one, even the Man Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; for ſo the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> hath plainly expreſſed it. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. <hi>For there is one God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and one Mediator between God &amp; Men; the Man Chriſt Jeſus, who gave himſelf a Ranſom for all, to be teſtified in due time.</hi> Therefore they, they ſet up to themſelves other Mediators, they are gone from the one Mediator which God hath appointed, and follow devices of their own Hearts, and the vain Traditions of men which will not profit them.</p>
            <p>Laſtly you give us all ground to think, that you are guilty to your ſelves, or at leaſt wiſe your Predeceſſors were guilty to themſelves of breaking the ſecond Commandment by your Images and Pictures; or elſe what need they have put it out of your Bibles, or out of the number of the ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? But it look't them ſo full in the Face that they were not able to behold it, and therefore expunged it out of your Bibles. It may be ſome may read it here, who never read it in their Bibles, therefore I will ſet it down here for them to read.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any graven Image, or the Likeneſs of any thing which is in the Heavens above or in the Earth beneath, or that is in the Water under the Earth. Thou ſhalt not bow down to them, nor worſhip them; for I the Lord thy God am a Jealous God, viſiting the Iniquity of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers upon the Children unto the third and fourth Generation of them that hate me, and ſhewing Mercy unto thouſnds of them that love me, and keep my Commandments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is that ſecond Commandment, which your Books want, becauſe your Practice will not bear it, its written <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.4,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63899:14"/>5, 6. If any be ſo bold as to ſay, there is no ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment; let them conſult with the <hi>Jews,</hi> and ask them whether their Bibles have it in or no; for they can give you certain Information in that point, and from them we have all received the old Teſtament.</p>
            <p>Thus I have in Faithfulneſs laid before you, what was repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to me from the Lord concerning your Condition. And God is my Witneſs, before whom I ſtand, that I have not writ theſe things in Malice or Wrath againſt you, or any Perſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, but in Faithfulneſs to your Souls, to let you ſee where you are.</p>
            <p>And if any of you continuing in your bloody Principles and bloody ſpirit (for you are noted for a bloody People) ſhall ſeek my Life for my Love to you, in dealing plainly with you, in leting you know the Truth, and ſo add that alſo to your Blood-guiltineſs, I value it not upon this Account, in Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Truth delivered to you, and of ſervice to your Souls therein. And therefore I ſubſcribe my Name, who am a Lover of Truth and Righteouſneſs, Meekneſs, Humility, Love and Faithfulneſs in whomſoever I find them, and of all whoſe Hearts are towards the Lord in Sincerity.</p>
            <byline>Written in the Year 1673. and in the 7th Moneth, By <hi>William Tomlinſon.</hi>
            </byline>
            <trailer>THE END,</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
